I know it's been a long day for everyone
and looking over the chat
it's a bit of a tough crowd, and I will
do my best to
present some new results --
this is actually the first time I will be
presenting this particular talk
and I hope it will be of practical
benefit to you, while
being not just one guy's opinion,
but based in academic research.
As Rafael mentioned,
I'm the Founder and CEO of Sweetwater
Digital Asset Consulting.
I see myself as bridging two very
separate worlds
which know very little about each other,
and, in fact, often times have little but
stereotype and prejudice to
cast the other in.  Those two worlds are
that of cypherpunk, cryptocurrency, open source
projects such as Monero or Bitcoin,
and then on the other side of this bridge,
is the traditional finance world, so as
Rafael mentioned, I was head of research
at a hedge fund and
so that is what I prepared my remarks to
to cover today.
Here's a taxonomy of assets.  These are
all the things that are out there that
are possible to invest in for
those who have wealth to invest.
And I’m dividing this into two rows:
there's fungible and non-fungible.
So, roughly, fungible means
that you don't care which thing you get
because from your point of view, all the
things that you could get are all
the same.  So if you look the fungible
bottom row here, we're looking at
cash and precious metals, so if you have
gold you can always melt it down.
There's no history associated with any
piece of gold, and so
from your point of view as long as you
know that something is gold, you don't
care where it came from.  Gold is gold.
It's fungible.
In the decentralized world, the
leader in that market segment is
currently Monero.
There's also non-fungible, which is on
the top, and that is,
you do care which particular unit of
value that you're getting,
because they're not the same.
So, let's think about real estate or
artworks.  If you have a plot of land,
there's presumably reasons that you
chose that plot of land,
and it's not really cool for you to just
get whatever
plot of land that comes out of some grab
bag or something.
Land is not fungible.  And it's the same
with works of art.
So, Bitcoin falls in that category, in that
there's a record -- a digital record -- that
is really etched in stone,
of everybody who had a piece of that
value in the Bitcoin blockchain
before you did.  And so, for people who
have a squeaky clean reputation,
who have worked hard, played by the rules
their whole life --
they want to be insulated from the
potential misdeeds of other people who
are on that same network.
Which means that Bitcoin is going to
fail these people.
Bitcoin is going to fail these people
because sometimes, these squeaky clean
people are going to deal with
other people on the Bitcoin blockchain
who are not as squeaky clean as they are.
And because in a surveillance coin --
a transparent coin like Bitcoin --
reputation transfers as well as value,
that means that the squeaky clean
person's reputation is going to be
besmirched,
by chance -- by having done some sort of
random financial transaction with someone on
the Bitcoin blockchain who's not as squeaky
clean as they are.
So a classic example would be: a squeaky
clean person has a car,
and they sell it to somebody for bitcoin,
and unbeknownst to them,
the person who they sold their car to
got their bitcoin
by dealing on the dark web, or some
nefarious activity.
So, it's a bit counterintuitive,
but the conclusion of this -- and this is
also supported by some
Nobel prize winning research in
economics, for example, the Akerloff
paper which studies [the]
behavior of participants in a market
when buyers and sellers have
different levels of information on
what's being traded --
the conclusion of that is that the
squeaky clean people are going to leave
that market,
in which their goodness, basically, is not
compensated for.
And they are going to go to a coin that
will protect them, like Monero.
But let's step back for a minute.  Let's talk
about fiat currency and scarcity in
general, and why is it that we even care
about cryptocurrency to start with.
The G20 is the collection of 20 of the
largest world economies.
What I’m showing here is the amount of
money supply that each of these countries
has out in circulation.  The left-hand
side of this plot is 2009, which is the
year that Bitcoin became a thing,
and this goes all the way to data that I
collected just a couple of days ago from the
Federal Reserve website.
And what I've done is that no matter how
big or how small
any country's currency is, they [are]
labeled as having a value of 1 at the
beginning of 2020.
And so what you can see is that every
fiat currency
in the world turned on the printing
presses at an accelerating rate
after the pandemic hit.
Before the pandemic,
there was even still reason for quite a
bit of concern because if you look,
this is 0.5 here, which means that in the
time period between 2012
and 2020, that eight year period, that's
a doubling of most countries'
fiat supplies.  If something doubles every
eight years,
then think about what the impact of that
is over your lifetime.  So, let's say the
average person
lives 80 years, then this doubling is
going to happen 10 times,
and when something doubles
a bunch of times, it gets big fast.  That's
exponential growth.  In this case, it would
be 2 to the 10th power, which is about
1,000.  So that's a 1,000 times
inflation in the money supply over one's
lifetime --
and that is using the rate of growth
before the pandemic.
After the pandemic we're looking at a
doubling time that's closer to
maybe two years.  The reason that it's
disguised a bit,
is that everybody else is doing it too.
So, if everyone else is doing it, then
we don't look quite as bad on a relative
basis with other countries.
However, since 2009, there has been such a
thing as decentralized scarcity.  There
has been a thing called Bitcoin, which
manufactured a way
to synthesize digital scarcity
without needing a central authority
to maintain that scarcity.
What I’m showing here is year-over-year
supply inflation.
In green, you're looking at how much
USD was there in one year versus the
year previous,
and I’m looking at MZM, which is a broad
measure of money supply which includes
checking, savings accounts, and money
market accounts --
there is a multiplier effect here if you
want to get technical -- but you know,
at the end of the day, all of these
measures of money supply show the same
thing:  there's a giant spike at the pandemic
and the giant spike has not gone away.
In contrast to that, let's look at these
alternate forms of scarcity that are not
controlled by a central government -- the
classic one being gold.
Now the World Gold Council does an
estimate of how much gold
is being dug out of the ground every year.
It's been inflating at about 1.8 percent
per year, and that's been pretty
consistent over the last 10 years, at least.
So now, let's plot against that the
corresponding inflation figures for
Bitcoin and Monero.  The thing with
cryptocurrencies is,
unlike even gold, it can be predicted
in advance what the inflation rate is
going to be in the supply of that currency.
So this is one of the big features of
cryptocurrency, is that
the [rate] of future coin emissions has been
programmed in advance,
and it's enforced by the entire network
of computers
that is helping to do the bookkeeping
for each respective network.
So, Bitcoin computers have programmed [in]
them this future inflation curve,
and the same with Monero.  And you can see
that we're coming in
on this inflection point here.
In mid-2021,
the rate of year-over-year supply
inflation is going to
cross that of gold,
and go [lower than] that of gold, and it will
remain lower than that of gold, forever.
Now in the Monero project, of course, as
you've heard all day, the big
kind of uniting ethos of the Monero
community is we want this form of scarce
value to be fungible.
In other words, it introduces all sorts
of "meatspace" level problems -- this is
social level problems --
when a source of value is completely
traceable.  First of all, it [invites] the
participation of these so-called chain
analysis companies,
whose job it is to try to analyze the
flow of funds
in a transparent chain, and basically
"dox" people.
But the thing is, they have incomplete
information of the economic activity on
the chain.
All they can see is that money
changed hands from person A to person B.
they have no knowledge of the context --
which means it's easy for them to come to
false conclusions.  So let's go back to that
example of the
car seller.  Somebody sells their car for
bitcoin, they receive bitcoin that came
from a drug dealer or some bad person.
Now the innocent person who sold their
car has a problem,
because these chain analysis people know
that a quote-unquote bad person supplied
the bitcoin that this innocent car seller
now has.
So now, when this innocent car seller
goes to put their bitcoin on an exchange
to sell it back for USD, they're going to
get flagged,
and be forced to defend themselves
against these accusations
that were made on incomplete,
partial information, by a third party, who is
looking at this blockchain data from afar,
and applying, basically, a social credit score
to every participant on that network,
providing that social credit score
to its customers,
which are going to be things like
exchanges, and so on --
and they're going to wash their hands of any
inaccuracies.  They'll say, "well, we did our
best -- we came up with a 72.3 percent
chance that this person was actually bad
and so, you know, if if that turns out to be
wrong, well, then, you know, sorry" --
but really they're not really that sorry
and the people who they are
surveilling and making these social
credit scores for,
have no recourse to clear up their name
in case they're falsely accused.
So again, in Monero, the ethos is
that the best solution
for humanity's needs is going to be a
fungible coin.
And it turns out that this is easier
said than done, because
digital assets have at their heart
strings of ones and zeros
which are obviously unique.  You can tell
one string of ones and zeros from
another string of ones and zeros.
And so, to effectively manufacture
fungibility out of something that is inherently
extremely easy to tell apart from one
another, that is, numbers --
it takes considerable ingenuity.
And it is not something that can just be
slapped on.  And so
what I’m showing in this chart here, in
the top, is the daily average bytes
per transaction that is taken up on the
Monero blockchain.
So this is how much disk space is taken up
when one person in Monero decides to
send Monero to somebody else
and you can see that it's gone through
some history here.
There was a innovation in
Monero called RingCT which sought to
keep confidential the amounts that are
sent between the sender and receiver
and even though this innovation caused
the size of transactions to go up over
an order of magnitude, the community
decided it was worth it to do it
then later on there was bulletproofs, which
is basically clever mathematics
which found that, oh, these cryptographic
proofs that we're using
to guarantee [the] integrity of the Monero system
while preserving the privacy of the
amounts transacted --
gee, there's a new way we can do that
that takes up a lot less byte space than
it used to.
That went through an audit process, and
after that came back, it was implemented.
And then you can see that the
transaction size went back down.
Now, last Halloween,
there was a new innovation [called] CLSAGs
that also went in, and that chipped
away at the transaction size a bit more.
The point being, that this community has
done what it takes
to make sure that fungibility is
in the blockchain, and improved in the
blockchain.  And there's continual
research happening on this front.
On the bottom we're looking at the daily
average transaction fee, in US dollars,
for both Bitcoin and Monero.  And you can
see that when bulletproofs went in at
the end of 2018,
not only did the transaction size drop
by [an] order of magnitude,
the transaction fee also dropped by
basically the same amount, and so today, to
make a transaction in Monero, the average
transaction [fee] is on the order of pennies,
US pennies.  And the median is actually
below one penny.
This is a chain that puts a high
priority on the needs of its users.
It's a "customer first" sort of mentality,
so, the thinking is that the users of
Monero might be people in
oppressive regimes who are trying to escape
a draconian, cruel government with their
lives and their life savings --
and they might need something to escape
that is truly fungible and not traceable.
It's people like that
who the developers are developing Monero for.
All right.  So, that
was a very quick summary of some of
my previous videos.
Anyone who starts from zero, and watches
these videos,
will be more informed than, I would say,
80 percent of the other people
who are dabbling [in cryptocurrency.]
The names of these videos are
"Monero:  Sound Money, Safe Mode"
and the one preceding that was called
"Monero Means Money."
I think it's quite rare for videos like
this to get [a] good reception,
both from developer types
for technical accuracy, as well as
non-technical types who appreciate the
clarity of the explanations.  These are
something I've worked
quite hard on and I don't mean to
really self-promote
but this is a recommendation, because in
the chat, I saw that there were
quite a few new people who could use a
kind of a solid
background level introduction to this stuff.
Volunteers in the Monero community have
graciously taken time to
translate the subtitles in this.
These videos have been,
or are in the process of being,
translated into several European languages.
Basically, we want this narrative that
fungibility and privacy in Monero is for
squeaky clean people too --
they are the ones who need it most.
And so, if that message is
is absent in any given [society],
you might have a tendency
for regulators to assume that
there are no squeaky clean people using
Monero, and we want to
avoid that misperception.
Because it is a misperception.
All right.  So now on to the new content
of this talk.  So
one thing you will hear, especially from
proponents of the number one market cap
crypto currently,
that is, Bitcoin -- one thing you will hear
a lot is this phrase, "the markets have spoken."
What we're looking at here is
coingecko.com.  What they do is they
get a list of all the cryptocurrency
projects out there;
they ask the question, "how many units of
value are out there?"
for each of these cryptocurrencies, and
what was the most recent trading price
for each of these units of scarcity, and
they multiply the two.
When you multiply those two you get a
measure called market cap,
and what that means is, roughly, what is
the value of all of the Bitcoin in the world?
So, if you were to take everyone's Bitcoin,
and put it in a giant pot, what would it
be worth?  Now of course, that's a difficult
question, because
if [only] one person had it, then its value
would automatically go down, because
there's a network effect.  But
the approximation of using the number of
units times the latest market price --
that's one of the better forms
of estimate that we have
for the value of a project.  And so this
website takes all of the [projects]
[and] it ranks them.
So, which cryptocurrency has the largest
market cap?  It's Bitcoin.
Number 2 is Ethereum, number 3 is Tether --
I would imagine, even if you're
new to cryptocurrency, you're
familiar with a list of this kind, and
this is a screenshot from earlier today,
and so now you...
you see down here at number 20,
is Monero.
So, you know,
if Monero has all these great characteristics,
well, why is it down at number 20 then?
And so, this is a question that comes up,
and as it happens, my previous background
in finance includes questions of this nature,
and so that's what I'd like to talk about.
So, the markets have spoken, or have they?
I know that this group is
quite familiar with the debate in
macroeconomics, that is political
economics, of Keynes versus Hayek,
so I won't go into that at all.
I'll assume that
you all are versed in at least the
basics of that
debate, which happens at a national kind
of political level,
at the macroeconomic level.
But, I don't know if
many are aware of this, because I
actually never hear crypto people talk
about this --
and so I hope that this is actually
something new and interesting in the
crypto space today --
and that is in microeconomics, there is a
similar debate that's going on,
and it has been going on for decades.
And this is,
neoclassical economics versus
behavioral economics.
So first, I'll define what I’m talking
about, then I'll give a few examples from the
traditional capital markets, and then
I'll move to the crypto markets.
So, neoclassical economics came first,
so I'll talk about that first.
It's the more "old school" version of the
world view,
and there are two assumptions, basically,
in neoclassical economics, and they are
the following:
people are rational -- that means every person
will maximize their own utility, and
utility is just
[an] economics word that you could replace
that with happiness --
people do what they can to maximize
their own happiness, given the
constraints that they face due to having,
you know, a certain budget that they have
to deal with.
Second, is that markets are efficient and
what that means is that
all of the information about any given
asset is encoded into the price.
And so there's no way to game the system at all.
The market price of every asset is
always the "correct" price
that incorporates all known information
about that asset.
Another way to say this, in the words of
Dr. Eugene Fama, who's a professor at the
University of Chicago,
and also was one of the recipients of
the Nobel in economics for
[furthering] theories along this point of view,
is to say that there are no bubbles;
there's no such thing as a bubble.
All right, the challenging view is
behavioral economics.
So, that is the following:
let's take that as a given --
OK, people are rational.
OK, let's take it as a given, markets
are efficient.  Now, let's also observe
that Wall Street makes up
21 percent of US [GDP].
So, now, something is a little fishy here,
so if people are so smart and rational,
why do they need this gigantic financial
sector to help them do anything?
If markets are so efficient why is there
so much sales, so much profit, to be made
in the financial sector?
Anyone sympathetic to the ethos of cryptocurrency
is going to, I think, agree quite
wholeheartedly with this.  One thing that
crypto has the potential to disintermediate
is this 21 percent of the US economy.
So, in the words of Dr. Richard Thaler,
also a University of Chicago
professor, who is one of the founders of
behavioral economics,
and also a Nobel prize winner -- he says,
"pick two."
So one of these assumptions has to be false --
that people are rational or markets are
efficient, or maybe both.
Now, I should add, just speaking as a
physicist, that when
economists modeled people to be these
rational, efficient, happiness maximizers,
why did they do that?  That [enabled] them
to use the language of mathematics
because
if you think about maximization problems,
there's a branch of calculus, for
example, variational calculus --
basically, tools in mathematics that can
be used to apply to the problem,
once you have this quantitative definition
of people's behavior as being
maximization of some function.
So that enabled economists to, kind of
become a science, so to speak, and take
the success of harder sciences like physics
in their quantitative
exploration of the way the world works.
The drawback of this is that, is it true?
Is it really true to make these assumptions?
So the behavioral economics worldview
breaks down like this:
"Econs" are rational, and "econs" are the
word for the fictitious, human-like forms
that are hypothesized in the old school
neoclassical economics.  So "econs," you
could think of like Dr. Spock, right?
They're [a] kind of robot people,
they make perfect decisions under data,
and they would never do anything to
sabotage their own self --
so "econs" are rational.  Markets that are
made of "econs" are efficient.
What behavioral economics does is to add
the following caveat:
actual people are dumber -- both dumber
in terms of intelligence, and nicer -- in
terms of altruism -- because one feature, I think,
that's evolved in humanity,
is that there's a sort of an innate
desire in many people
to kind of get along.  You don't want to
perpetually be at war with your neighbors.
You might do a nice thing for somebody
from time to time,
even though that might not be strictly
in your economic best interest,
like making a donation, or something like that.
These are aspects of human behavior that don't
really fit well with the view of
people being "econs."
All right, so in behavioral economics,
the observation is that actual people are both
dumber and nicer than "econs" --
and in predictable ways --
and so, that is the interesting part of this.
All right, so I’m going to give a couple examples of
how this shows up in capital markets but first,
I have to give a 101 of accounting.
So, the fundamental identity of
accounting is A = L + E.
You can think of that as "ALE," like the drink,
so that is a mnemonic to remember this.
What this is saying is that
every company -- or it could be a person, or
it could be a country,
it works at any sort of level -- but let's
just stick with the
example of a company.  A company is a
thing that has a bunch of assets --
it might have factories, and so on.  These
assets get divided into two parts.
There are people who that the company
owes money to.
It basically had to get a loan from the bank,
or if it's big enough, maybe it would
have issued its own corporate bonds.
Those are basically IOUs, those are liabilities.
And under corporate legal structure,
if a company goes bankrupt, and these
assets get sold,
then the liabilities must get paid first.
The people who
made loans of cold hard cash -- they must
be first in line to get the
pickings of the dead company's sold assets.
So whatever is not owed
to outside lenders, is the
property of the owners, and that is equity,
and this is the stock market.
So this is the bond market on top,
this is the stock market on bottom.
So they add up.
So you have a bunch of assets --
some of it is owed to money lenders, and
the rest is owned by the owners.
Shares of stock represent shares of
equity.  So if there's a million shares of
this company,
you think of this blue box now as being
divided into one million little [squares.]
Each one of those little squares gives
the owner of that share of stock
the right to the [one-millionth] share of profits
that company management decides to spit out
to the shareholders, and these are called dividends.
So now you think of the assets as being
like a factory, you have a factory that makes
computers or something like that --
as it makes the computers, customers
are pumping in
money to pay for those computers,
so the cash is part of these assets --
so one thing the management [can do]
is to elect to
plow those assets back into the company
to grow it --
but another thing that the company could
do, is if it doesn't have any smart
plans to expand the company,
it can spit out that [cash]
back to the owners, which is the form of dividends.
All right.  So, are prices always right?
And there are four challenges
to that notion, from empirical evidence,
that I’m going to show.
The first one is from Robert Shiller,
who got the Nobel in
2013 for this work.  Basically what
Dr. Shiller showed was, here you're
looking at actual stock prices in blue,
and in red, you're looking at what the
stock price should have been
if the stock owner had known
what the next 30 years of dividends was
going to look like for that stock.
So, if you buy a share of Tesla right now,
you don't know if dividends are going to
be paid on that stock, ever.
It could be 10 years from now, it
could be 20 years from now, you don't know --
but you're buying it partly because you
think that Tesla is going to do so well in the future
that it's going to have extra cash
that it would be able to
send to you in the form of dividends.
So what this study is saying
is that even if you had perfect advance
knowledge of how much dividends would be
coming your way as a shareholder,
If you had perfect knowledge
you would price the stock like this
dotted red line.
But what the market actually did was
price the stock like this blue line.
In other words there are huge differences
between a quote-unquote fair value and
what the market determines to be the
fair value, and you can see here that
these periods of inflation, inflated prices,
can last for decades -- it's not necessarily the
case that -- oh, there's a short-term
blip in the price.
Another example, and this one I was directly
involved with, actually -- so there was a
paper called "Liquidity as an Investment Style"
and I was a co-author of this with [Prof.] Roger
Ibbotson at the [Yale] School of Management --
it did get some play, it won an award
for being the "paper of the year"
in the Financial Analysts Journal
-- that was given by the CFA
Institute, which is kind of the
credentialing body for
investment analysts in the US, and
actually, around the world --
that award got picked up by The Economist,
which is a UK news magazine --
and so here's a chart that
I helped to make --
and what this is showing is:
let's say you take US stocks,
and you sort them into four bins.
The method that you use
to determine which bin
each stock goes in is:  you look at the
previous year,
and you ask the question, how much
trading volume happened in that stock
over the last year?
So, if it had a lot of
trading volume you'd put it into the
4th, the highest bin of trading volume.
Whereas, if you have a stock that's basically
ignored -- nobody cares about it, nobody
talks about it, everyone thinks
it's not cool to talk about it --
that would go in the 1st bucket here.
And what we find,
is that if you look at [the] following
year's return of that stock,
you see this pattern:  that the ignored
and forgotten stocks are the ones that
will outperform in future years as opposed to
the "hot stocks" that everyone knows
and everybody talks about,
and everybody trades.
So, that's another very interesting kind
of behavioral thing, and it invites
kind of a theory of popularity
in which you have unpopular things
which everyone has ignored and forgotten
about, and as a result, the price goes
down, because nobody
cares about it.  Then, in the future, some
news happens --
it becomes hot in the future, and when it
becomes hot, when it becomes
talked about, then the price goes up and
that is what is
explaining these high returns here.
And the opposite happens.  So if you have
some "flavor of the day" kind of stock
that everyone's talking about,
those are the ones that you actually
want to avoid,
you want to have a caution flag on those --
because those
tend to have their day in the sun,
you find out about it while it's having its
day in the sun,
then its day in the sun is gone,
its 15 minutes [of fame] are gone --
when the interest goes away, then the price
goes down too.
The dot-com bubble was a time in history
when the Internet was new.
In case there are maybe younger people
in the audience who didn't live through
the dot-com bubble,
it was a very interesting time because
if you had any sort of company
that had any sort of stupid idea, and you
added "dot com" to the end of the company name,
people would go crazy for it because it
was using this hot new thing called the
"Internet" --
which was brand spanking new, back then.
And so there was this company called pets.com,
and its idea was to
FedEx 50 pound bags of dog food to people
and charge grocery store prices
even though they were, you know, taking a
bath on the shipping -- but!
But, they were using the Internet to
take their orders.
And so this was a hot company,
they went through an IPO,
it actually got investment from
amazon.com, if you can believe that,
and it's an example of how
a new technology can promote
inefficiency in pricing.
In other words -- when you have a new
technology that is not very well understood
among the people, that is the time when
everyone's going to take their stupid idea,
add "dot com," and advertise it as being the
next best thing since sliced bread.
And, so, of course -- [a] very similar thing is
happening with blockchain, right?
So take any sort of idea you can
possibly think of -- doesn't matter
how stupid it is -- and you make it a
blockchain thing,
you issue an ICO,
you know, you might do okay.
Finally:  are prices always right?
Well, if you
accept the efficient market hypothesis,
then, yes, prices are always right.
But let's look at
just a few years ago.  So, now, we're not
talking about the [90s when] the Internet was
new, we're talking just
four years ago, three and a half years ago.
This is what the market cap list
looked like in late October 2017,
and you can see number 8 here,
there's this thing called Bitconnect.
And again, if you are new to the crypto space,
you should study this.
You should study this total scam Ponzi scheme
called Bitconnect,
which managed to become number 8
on the ranking charts
as far as cryptocurrency.
Part of their
official website actually included this pyramid
It would be hard for them to [make it] more
obvious that this was a pyramid scheme.
And this particular date, October 28, 2017,
was the date when this
video which became a sort of classic meme
in crypto, came out, in which this
gentleman here
did very little but scream "Bitconnect"
into a microphone
and people thought it was great.
So, of course, you had this ironic
section of crypto people who kind of
laughed at it and thought it was a big joke --
but, you know, this is real money!  This is
like, one and a half billion dollars that
people ended up losing to this fraud.
Be careful.
So, is a current
high market cap indicative of merit?
I'll ask it again: are prices always right?
In 1936, Keynes, the economist --
going back to the
first slide about Keynes versus Hayek --
this is one politically neutral
observation that he had, and this was
pertaining a newspaper contest that was
published in 1936.
And so what this contest did was it
published one [hundred]
photos of [attractive] people.
So, 100 photos and 100 names on them --
and it said, okay, we're going to do a contest here
and what we want you to do is,
you pick the six prettiest
people on this page,
you write their names down,
and you send it into our newspaper.
The winner of this contest is going to
be whoever it is
who chose the most popular pretty photos.
So now, Keynes' observation was this:
what is your best strategy?  Is your best
strategy to actually pick the six
photos that you think are the prettiest?
That would be maybe your first reaction.
But if you think about it a bit more,
you might have weird taste, right?
You might have taste
that is not reflective
of everybody else.  So, the second
iteration of your strategy would be:
I'm going to pick the six people
who I think everybody else thinks is pretty.
so basically you imagine
what the population
thinks they're gonna like and you're
going to guess that.  You can even take
that a step further:  you can say,
well, that's okay, but
other guys are going to do that too so
what I need to do, is I need to
think about the people who are thinking
about everybody else
and selecting what they
think the 6 prettiest.. right, so it
gets very circular,
gets very complicated, [and] Keynes'
observation was
that this is really what the stock
market is like.  It's not
direct merit that price is capturing,
it's a derivative of it.  And it has
an estimation of what you think everyone
else is thinking, in it.
So that leads to this quote here:  "In the
short run, the market is a voting machine,
but in the long run,
it is a weighing machine."
In the short run it's a popularity contest,
and popularity contests can have winners
that are not necessarily the most
[meritorious] --
but in the long run, those kind of popularity
fads are going to come and go, and what
you're left with is merit, in the long term.
All right.  So, [in] behavioral economics
there was one
particularly important Nobel prize that
pinpointed two very specific things
that people do that are not rational.
If you don't know these, this is,
I would say, among the most important
discoveries, I'd say, of the
20th century, I mean this is
important to know, and not everyone knows it.
So if you know it, and other people don't,
you're gonna have a bit of an edge on them.
This is called prospect theory, and the
reason it's called prospect theory
is that it talks about how people make decisions
about their future prospects.  They have
two main observations:  number one,
people perceive the pain of loss more intensely
than equally sized gains.  So, going back
to the "econ," this
Dr. Spock character who the
[neo]classical economics is based on --
this classic character, like basically a robot --
if you go up to a robot and say,
we're going to flip a coin, if it comes
up heads I’m going to give you a dollar,
if it comes up tails, I’m going to take a
dollar from you -- then the robot should
think that's a neutral game,
they should not really have an opinion
on it.  But if you go to a human
and do that -- if I were to come up to you,
and say, "we're going to flip a coin, if
it's heads, I’m giving you a dollar, if it
tails, I’m taking a dollar from you" --
now think of what's going to happen when
we do that game, and it comes up heads --
I give you a dollar,
and you say, "oh okay, great, thanks...
I won a dollar."
Let's say it comes out the opposite --
I take a dollar from you.  Well, you know,
our friendship might be over, basically.
You might not invite me to lunch next time.
Things like that are processed
by a different part of the brain than
the part of the brain that processes reward.
It's basically a more primal part of the
brain that is processing
negative [consequences.]  And there could
be evolutionary basis for this.
So, imagine caveman 1
walks by a tiger cave and says,
"oh, there's only a one percent chance that
the tiger's in there and it's going to eat me.
So, you know, I’m going to go -- because you
know, it's just a one percent chance" and
then they get eaten.
Caveman B walks by the same cave and
says, "oh, there's a tiger in there.  There's no
way I’m getting anywhere near that.
I don't care what the probability is."  So
basically it could be that the people who
overemphasized threats were the ones who
survived evolutionarily.
So, neoclassical person --
here, I’m showing a utility curve.  On the
horizontal axis, we're looking at something like
wealth -- so this is how much wealth you have --
have and on the vertical axis we're
talking about how happy you are
with your wealth.  And,
what you see for neoclassical person is
[the] law of diminishing returns,
which you might be
familiar with from economics --
that says:  if you have sat through a long day
of nine talks at a crypto conference
then the additional value to you of the 10th talk
(which happens to be my talk today, number 10)
is not going to be that much better.
You don't get that much additional
happiness out of that talk number 10.
That is why this curve flattens out.
It never starts going down -- it's never
the case that more wealth makes you less happy
it's that the rate of happiness increase
slows down as you get richer.
All right, so this is neoclassical robot person.
How do actual people behave?
The behavioral function looks like this, in which
it matters where your current level is.
If your current level is here on wealth,
then you will act rationally about that one
additional dollar.  But if you think about
the prospect of one dollar being taken from you,
now that's a different situation, you
become much less happy.
And, in fact, it turns out to be about
twice as unhappy.
So basically, a one dollar loss makes you
approximately the same emotional
reaction as a two dollar gain.
So this is a key insight and
it's something to know that you might be
doing when you are thinking about potential
losses. They will be magnified in your brain.
Prospect theory, the second part, is that
people crudely approximate probabilities
into three categories.
So here I’m plotting on the horizontal
axis is an actual probability of
something happening,
and on the vertical axis, this is the
perceived probability -- this is what a human being
thinks the probability is, in their brain,
when they're deciding what to do.
So neoclassical
robot person here has no bias.
Whataver the actual probability is,
that's going to be the exact perception
of the probability, and they will act rationally.
How do actual people behave?
Actual people tend to
categorize probabilities into three
crude buckets.
Those buckets are:  "never going to happen,"
"maybe" -- so, basically a 50-50 coin flip --
and "for sure."
So, if something has a one percent chance
of happening, people often will simply
simplify that, and say, "never going to happen" --
or, you could have people who
round up -- and say that one percent chance
is going to happen like 50-50.
So it turns out that
people are pretty bad at assessing
probabilities, and it turns out
that what you would think of as standard
measures of intelligence --
they will not exempt a genius from being
susceptible to this bias.
It happens to them too.
All right, so let's apply that.  OK, I'm
the insurance company
and I’m going to offer you -- because
planes are scary, and dangerous, and they
could fall out of the sky, you know,
it's been known to happen --
so we're going to offer you this $100,000
insurance policy,
and we will pay that if your plane crashes.
What is the actual probability of that
happening?  Well, of course,
you know, it's going to be very, very,
small -- it's about 1 in 10 million.
Let's say you charge one penny for that
insurance policy,
as the insurance company.
That means 10 million times,
people are going to [pay a] penny.
One of those times out of the 10 million,
somebody's going to crash, and you as the
insurance company, are going to have to pay
out the $100,000.
The ten million pennies that you collected --
that is the same as $100,000.
In other words,
the $100,000 you collected
as premiums, is the same as the
$100,000 you paid out, as a [claims] payment.
So the fair [price] for an insurance policy
like this is one penny.
Why do they sell this?
They sell this because they
know that there's a subset of people
who are going to take that one in a million
probability,
and in their minds, instead of rounding
it down to the "never" bucket,
because it's a fear, they're going to
round that probability
up to the "maybe" bucket.
This is an exaggerated perception of
loss -- so that's the first part of
prospect theory remember?
So if you're thinking about a loss
versus a gain, your brain is going to
magnify the badness of that bad thing.
It's like little kids,
being [scared of a] monster under the covers --
your imagination's going to come up
[with] something crazy and [because it's]
a bad thing, you're going to magnify
the importance of that,
or the likelihood of that.
So, in this case,
the person that they're targeting --
the customer type that
an insurance company like this is trying
to make a buck off of --
is the type of person who has an
exaggerated perception of loss,
and so their perceived probability of a crash
gets rounded up, to the "maybe" bucket,
instead of the "never going to happen" bucket.
So, let's say this person now thinks that
they have a 1 in 1,000
chance of being in a plane crash.
Every 1,000 flights, they're going to die once.
And so, if they think that, then it's
going to be worth $100 to them
to have a policy that pays $100,000 upon death.
And so, of course, this company's going to
price their thing at, like $50 --
you know, it's grossly overpriced for the
insurance that they're offering --
but they're going to be enough suckers
to make it a profitable thing.
This is an example of a predatory use of
the natural human tendency to have these biases.
But my purpose in this talk is to try to
get you to think about ways you could
be aware of this.  So, as you continue on
in your education
in the crypto space, you're aware of
these biases -- both in yourself
and in other people that you talk with.
All right, so I was saying that these
biases happen to quote-unquote smart
people, as well as
not-so-smart people, so here's the
example of Long-Term Capital Management.
This was a hedge fund
in Connecticut, also in the mid-90s,
and if you wanted [a] blue-ribbon panel of
smart people on your hedge fund,
this one had it.  This one had Scholes, you
might have heard of Black-Scholes, that is
the famous formula that was
derived by Scholes to determine a fair price for
options, and that was also a Nobel prize winning
innovation -- and so these gentlemen were
both on the board of directors.
And as you can see in the blue line, the
performance of this hedge fund
was fantastic for a while -- and then it
crashed.  And one of the things that they
lost on was the Russian default
on Russian bonds that happened in mid-1998.
Long-term Capital Management
had the logic of the following:
the Russian [government]
owe money on these bonds that they paid,
but these bonds were not denominated in
dollars, or euros, or whatever --
these bonds were
denominated in Russian rubles,
and the Russians had the printing
presses to their own rubles --
so what's the probability that the
Russians are going to
default on those bonds, it's got to be
zero, because they own the printing presses
to the thing that they have to pay back.
It's kind of as if you had a
mortgage on your house
and to pay back the mortgage, you were
allowed to pay it back with "Monopoly
money" that you printed out on your
inkjet printer --
it's the same situation.  So, of course, why
would they default -- and it turns out they
defaulted.
So, this was a case of oversimplifying a probability
they thought of the probability of
default as being so small it was
negligible and they rounded it down to zero
when they shouldn't have.
So, this happens to everybody --
but not you, because you're watching this talk.
How can you apply this in crypto?
so, in crypto, there's a lot of "FUD" --
F-U-D, and that stands for fear, uncertainty
and doubt.
And so this is basically slander that
often comes out against one crypto
project or another.
And, part of your job as you navigate
cryptocurrency is to make sense of this --
what are you going to do with it?
you can't just ignore it,
you have to evaluate it somehow --
but often times these are things that are
difficult to prove,
and, so, what are you going to do?
What you want to do
is be aware that you're going to have an
innate tendency
to say, "eh... won't happen" or
"oh yeah, that's going to happen" or "eh...
it's a coin flip, it might happen."
That's going to be your tendency.
You need to be aware of that.  Because
if you give in to that --
that can be an expensive decision
because the actual probabilities matter.
The fair value of any asset is the sum
of the probability of every possible
future outcome
times that future value.
Know that you're going to tend to oversimplify the
probability, and resist that impulse.
And you should also know that because
it's fear, uncertainty, and doubt, they're
designed to trigger that loss impulse in your mind,
so it's going to get magnified in your brain.
So, I would say to try to think about it
clinically, think about it objectively,
think of it like
some sort of math problem that your
challenge is to estimate the probability
of some event happening.
As a example for this, I would like to
talk about --
and I saw this in the chat earlier --
what's the probability that the whole
world bans Monero?
Now, so we saw an interesting talk from
Justin [Ehrenhofer] earlier that had
kind of a takeaway message that
it's not obvious that a given country --
for example, the United States --
will want to ban Monero from centralized
exchanges, because then it's going to lose a bunch
of information that it would have otherwise
been able to access, by being able to
regulate that exchange.
If it bans it, then all the trading is going to
go to forums that it has
no information in.
So, it actually might be
in the best interest of a given government
to allow it.
So now I want to take that one [step] further,
I want to look at the entire world, right?
So, [an] effective worldwide ban
would need to be coordinated, globally.
It wouldn't really work for one country to say,
"OK, we're going [to ban] Monero"
and everyone else is like "yeah, whatever,
it's still cool here."  [That's] not much of a ban.
You have to have
everyone, like, on board, right?
You've got to coordinate this, and then on
some day you've got to be like "OK, we
world governments have all come to the
conclusion that we're doing this ban."
All the important countries would
need to participate.
So certainly, you'd think of the big ones --
the US, the Eurozone,
China and Russia.  So, immediately,
here are four countries that don't have
[a] consistent record in all getting along
and singing Kumbaya on anything.
But, beyond that -- each of these countries
has to choose,
"ban" or "no ban."  Each country,
as a sovereign unit, they get to choose,
"do we cooperate in this worldwide ban, or
do we not cooperate?"
So, the cooperating option I’m putting in green,
and the non-cooperative option, I’m
putting in red.  So if everyone in the
world bans it,
all the world governments -- OK, they say,
"hooray, no more Monero."
However, let's say one or more countries
do not go along with this scheme
and they elect to not ban.
So, they say "no ban."  What's going to happen?
Then, the countries that did a
"no-ban" --
they're going to get an incoming influx
of brain power
working on this form of fungible,
decentralized, digital value.
Now, all of a sudden -- maybe this is
not what the "ban" people were thinking.
They were not intending
for a reward in global innovation
to go to the countries that were not cooperating.
And yet this is a classic problem in game theory.
it's called the prisoner's dilemma problem.
The prisoner's dilemma problem goes like
this:  you have two suspects,
and they've been captured by the police,
and they've been detained,
and now they're being interrogated in
separate rooms, so they can't talk to
each other.
So, you have "perp 1" and "perp 2."
Each of these detained people can decide:
am I going to rat on the other guy?  Am I
going to tell the police that the other
guy did it?
Or, am I going to keep my mouth shut, and
not betray my "partner in crime" here --
that's the decision that each of these people have.
What is the outcome based on what they
do?  So, if neither of these
suspects rat, then they both go free,
because the police didn't get any
confessions out of any [of them.]
If they both rat on each other, they both
stay in jail.
The interesting situation happens if one
of the guys
decides to betray his chum, but the other
guy does not choose to betray.  That is,
"rat" and "no rat."  What happens then?
Then the "dishonorable" person -- the rat --
gets to go free,
because his buddy didn't blame him --
he gets to go free.  The guy who was
actually doing the quote unquote
honorable thing,
by sticking with his teammate -- he's going
to stay in jail.
This is called the prisoner's dilemma.
OK, so I’m pointing out that a global
ban on Monero is kind of like the
prisoner's dilemma --
but is there any more real world data
that we can use
to put a little more light on this question?
And the answer is yes -- it turns out that
in the 90s,
there was a game show called "Golden Balls."
You can go on YouTube and watch some
episodes of this -- but basically, the
end of every episode of "Golden Balls" was
a prisoner's dilemma.
You have two finalists, and each one can choose:
"do I steal the jackpot, or do I split the jackpot?"
And the jackpot [size would] vary, it was usually
1,000 to 100,000 British pounds,
so that'd be like 2,000 to 200,000 US dollars,
although towards the end of that period,
it would have been 1,500 to 150,000 US dollars --
so basically, if the two contestants
agree to be nice to each other --
if they go "split" ["split"] -- then each contestant
wins half the money.
If one person is dishonorable, and
chooses to steal,
but the other person is nice, then the
stealer wins all the money,
the nice person gets nothing.  And if they
both choose to steal,
the TV show keeps the entire jackpot.
And, so, a picture being worth a thousand
words, these are very entertaining --
here are two ladies, and they both said
they were going to "split" --
and so they both go home winners,
it's like a daughter and mother
finding the daughter and the mother that
they never had, all of a sudden --
a very heartwarming moment.
Here's one where the woman on the left
has chosen to steal the entire jackpot
from the shell-shocked man on the right
who is revealing that his decision was [to] split --
they have these golden balls, one has the
word "steal" and one has the word "split" in it,
so that's one
source of the name "Golden Balls" --
so the look of betrayal and shock on
the guy who is nice, but now is going
to go home with nothing,
contrasts with the... well, of course,
she's jumping up and down inside,
because she stole the entire jackpot, but
on the downside, she's being exposed on
national TV as being
somewhat of a twit -- and is finding it
difficult to look this guy in the eye.
And then here, we have a case of two stealers --
here you can see that they were both
revealing that they were planning to
stab each other in the back
and the faces kind of say a lot.
So that's all very entertaining -- but
what's really fascinating was that there
was an academic paper that studied
all of the 150 final rounds of "Golden Balls,"
and they did an analysis:  what makes the
contestants more likely to cooperate
versus not cooperate?
And so the key result from this paper
I’m showing here, is this:
that as the jackpot went up -- so that's
the horizontal axis on this plot, so
as you go from 100 pounds to 1,000
pounds to a 100,000 pounds,
you're going to the right --
and then on the vertical axis, this is
the probability that the two
contestants were nice to each other, and
did a "chop chop," a "split split" of the pot --
and both went home happy.
You can see when the
pot was like, 10 pounds, they're like,
"yeah, OK, we'll just split it" right?
It's not worth looking like a jerk on
national TV -- but once you get into the
quote-unquote life-changing amounts of
100,000 pounds --
now, the probability that each one is
going to go home with half of it goes down
because they observe that if they're greedy
they could go home with even more.
What does this inform us with the
prisoner's dilemma problem,
as applied to a global ban on
cryptocurrency?  It is that as the
perceived value of cryptocurrency increases,
a global ban is going to become less likely,
because any country that doesn't
cooperate with the ban
is going to capture
more of the economic value
that comes with being a beacon of freedom
that would allow, basically, smart geeks
to come settle in, and help build this new
economy with this efficient new form of money.
So basically, since the price of crypto
keeps getting more valuable, this is
saying that game theoretically, a global
ban becomes less likely as time goes on.
All right, so there are a lot more
examples of things like this, but I'll stop here.
Here's my summary of behavioral crypto.
Market prices are not always correct.
You should keep that in mind.
Especially for any widely misunderstood
new technology --
in 1993, that was the Internet --
it's happening again now.
One question that is unresolved that
happened in the dot com era:
in the dot com era, there was kind of a
battle that was forming between two
visions of what the Internet would be.
One was a "Wild West" of the open Internet,
in which you could just get on with a
browser, and type whatever you wanted
in the address bar, and it would take you
there.  That was just "Wild West"
because anyone could put up a website,
anyone could do whatever they want,
and anyone was free to go wherever
they want -- that was like this
crazy world that was envisioned.
That was kind of one
direction that the Internet could have gone.
The other was
exemplified by a company called America Online,
AOL, and what they offered was a "walled
garden" sort of experience.
So basically, you would not be on the
Internet if you were an AOL customer.
You would be on AOL's curated version of
the Internet:  "OK, I’m going to take away
your Mozilla web browser, and I’m just
going to give you this other app,
and you'll be able to choose
websites that we... approved... for you,
you'll be happy with it, you'll like it" --
people didn't want it.
People wanted the wide open Wild West.
But we're in a point in crypto that is
very like that crossroads that was in the
internet in the mid-90s:
that is, do we want an open
blockchain, you have a Wild West
of different projects out there with
different ethos?
Or do you have AOL -- so you would go to a
custodian, and the custodian would take care of all
these crypto choices for you, and they'd
serve it up to you on a
sanitized little platter that you could then click
and choose from.  So, we're in a similar
situation now -- it's not
really clear what's going to win.
All right, so part of behavioral
economics is the observation that people
tend to overemphasize
losses compared to gains.
They also tend to oversimplify
probabilities into three buckets:
"yes," "no," and "maybe."
"Smart" people have these biases too.
It's funny, if you look at the
general tenor of people's tweets or
whatever, they tend to get more and more
confident and then more and more
arrogant as the price goes up.
So, currently the price of Bitcoin's been up.
Over time, these mispricing biases tend
to resolve.  That is,
even though there can be temporary
dispositions in the "true" price versus a
market price, these tend to go away over time.
That is,
if you know that other people are biased,
and they're making estimates of
valuation based on biased estimators,
you know that they're biased and you
think you have a better version of it --
if you're right, that's an investing strategy.
In fact, we call this value investing.
This is exemplified by Benjamin Graham,
whose quote I read earlier,
but [of] course the most famous
proponent of this style of investing is
Warren Buffett.
Basically, what Warren Buffett does is he
looks for companies that nobody cares about,
they've been forgotten,
they're doing something that's not sexy,
they're doing something that's all fuddy-duddy,
not very exciting -- and
he sees that their prices are low, and
and he loads up on them, and he waits.
All right, so that's all I have --
put the earphones back in...
if you'd like to get in touch with me --
if you're looking for, maybe,
a Sherpa who can help you
kind of align your strategy with
principles based on
academic finance but also based on real
world experience --
also, a solid connection, like I mentioned
before, between the worlds of
open-source, cypherpunk cryptocurrencies
and the more traditional
aspects of wealth management, estate
planning, trusts --
so trusts are a potential way that you
can change the jurisdiction of your assets,
in a 100 percent legal and upfront way --
things like this are what I can help my
clients with.  So -- that's it, thanks.